Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's דף Daf is ק"ב, Kuf
Beis, 102,
and we pick up at the bottom, very bottom of ק"א עמוד
ב', Kuf Aleph Amud Beis, basically exactly on
target.
Okay, so אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
these two words left at ק"א עמוד ב'. Kuf Aleph Amud Beis.
So we started in with around חליצה Chalitzah and whether חליצה Chalitzah
needs a בית דין Beis Din of three or five, and the
גמרא's Gemara's conclusion was that it needed a בית דין Beis Din
of three, but nevertheless, we have some stories about רבנים Rabbanim who
made sure that there would be five for the purpose of לפרסומי
מילתא, Lefirsumei Milsa, to make it a more public matter, which might
have informed why רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said that halachically it required
five because part of the role of the בית דין, Beis Din,
as we said here, how much is it to adjudicate and how
much is it to kind of represent כלל ישראל? Klal Yisrael? ונקרא
שמו בישראל, V'nikra shemo b'Yisrael, which was something that the גמרא Gemara
said earlier and said that that's why the בית דין Beis Din
itself have to say חלוץ הנעל Chalutz Ha'na'al because they are representing
the community. So even if halachically three suffices, we saw that those
who required the five, and the גמרא Gemara ended with a story
that
they called a rabbi to come and participate and he said, "No,
I can't participate, I'm a גר," Ger, and because one of the
things we also learned was בישראל, B'Yisrael, and therefore if בישראל B'Yisrael
is the בית דין Beis Din and the בית דין Beis Din
is representing ישראל, Yisrael, that is understood to mean naturally born ישראל
Yisrael and not גרים Geirim and I can't be a part of
it. Again what was interesting was he was only asked to be
part of the additional two, they already had the core three, and
this was only being done לפרסומי מילתא. Lefirsumei Milsa. Nevertheless, they wanted
to construct it, you know, conceptually that the five, the entire five,
was being seen of as a type of an expanded בית דין.
Beis Din. So even to be part of numbers four and five,
he didn't want to be because of this idea of a
בית דין Beis Din of
naturally born
ישראל. Yisrael. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to turn for
a moment to focus on this issue of a גר Ger serving
on a בית דין, Beis Din, and then it's going to turn
back to the יבום Yibum issues. So let's take a look at
the bottom of ק"א עמוד ב'. Kuf Aleph Amud Beis.
אמר רבא. Amar Rava. Okay, now we'll go to the top of
ק"ב. Kuf Beis. אמר
רבא גר דן את חבירו דבר תורה.
Amar Rava Ger dan es
chaveiro devar Torah. A גר, Ger, although we said before that a
גר Ger couldn't be on a בית דין, Beis Din, a גר
Ger could judge a fellow גר Ger biblically speaking, שנאמר, Shene'emar, and
even rabbinically speaking, שום תשים עליך מלך אשר יבחר ה' אלוקיך בו
מקרב אחיך תשים עליך מלך לא תוכל לתת עליך איש נכרי אשר
לא אחיך הוא.
Som tasim alecha melech asher yivchar Hashem Elokecha bo
mikerev achecha tasim alecha melech lo tuchal lases alecha ish nochri asher
lo achecha hu.
So this is understood מקרב אחיך, Mikerev achecha, אחיך Achecha meaning your
biological brother, you know, somebody naturally born Jew, not a foreigner, even
a foreigner who is now a Jew cannot be a king. And
that's understood to say not only about a king but it's about
being on a בית דין. Beis Din. Now why being on a
בית דין? Beis Din? So רש"י Rashi gives two explanations. If you
take a look at רש"י Rashi at the last narrow line, הגר
אפילו חבירו, Hager afilu chaveiro, רש"י Rashi says דיין בכלל מלך דכתיב
מלך במשפט יעמיד ארץ אם דומה דיין למלך שאינו צריך כלום יעמיד
ארץ. Dayan bichlal melech dechtiv melech b'mishpat ya'amid aretz im domeh dayan
l'melech she'eino tzarich klum ya'amid aretz. Okay,
so number one is if a king establishes the land with justice,
so the judges are part of that whole system of
justice and the idea of a judge being independent and not being
dependent on people and therefore being able to be influenced, to have
that type of independence of a king. So therefore seeing that this
פסוק Pasuk is about מלך Melech is also referring to a judge,
so trying to say a judge has specific מלך Melech types of
roles and qualities and that's why he's in the פסוק. Pasuk. And
then רש"י Rashi says the more natural thing based on people that
have, you know, seen the other סוגיא Sugya in the גמרא, Gemara,
ועוד שימות הרבה הכתובים כאן, V'od simot harbeh haksuvim kan, כל שימות
שאתה משים לא יהא אלא מקרב
אחיך. Kol simot she'atah mesim lo yehei ela mikerev achecha. שום תשים
עליך מלך Som tasim alecha melech means all positions of appointed authority
have to be מקרב אחיך, Mikerev achecha, have to be
from a naturally born Jew. So of course the question is what
is defined as a position of authority, right? And this is a
whole סוגיא Sugya that we had more than a month ago, two,
three months ago about this about גרים Geirim in position of authority,
what exactly constitutes that? I'll just say על רגל אחת Al regel
achas because this is not the focus right now, the focus now
is בית דין, Beis Din, but you know רב משה Rav Moshe
was asked
about can a גר Ger be a ראש ישיבה? Rosh Yeshiva? Is
that a position of authority? Because he has the authority, exactly. Exactly.
So he says, you know, he's got the authority. This was even
about, I think, like a high school or something. He's got the
authority to decide who comes into, who's admitted into the school, who
does he kick out of the school, you know, what types
of
disciplinary actions. Sounds like he's got authority. So can a גר ger
be a ראש ישיבה? Rosh Yeshiva? And רב משה Rav Moshe basically
said that look, there's a הלכה halacha that a care— you can't
have an appointed position of authority, but there's also a מצוה mitzvah
of אהבת הגר. ahavas hager. And he says— it was a fascinating
case. He says the מצוה mitzvah of אהבת הגר ahavas hager compels
us, pushes us, to interpret the restriction of positions of authority as
narrowly as possible because the מצוה mitzvah of אהבת הגר. ahavas hager.
And therefore רב משה Rav Moshe says, so he starts with that,
says, you know, you can't just say okay, therefore it's not a
problem, but that's what's pushing us. And the conclusion he reaches is
that basically pretty much in like today's society where any type of
relationship you get into like this is one that is entered into
volitionally and contractually, so nobody really has a position of real authority.
You know, it's like a type of relationship that you freely entered
into and you sort of gave that person that right to make
those types of decisions by choosing to go to the school and
so on. And therefore it's not like, you know, a king, you
know, in an authoritarian society that compels something on you, against your
will. So, does that mean because people choose?
It's a contractual— what do you—
Yeah,
like if I choose to go to this school, then I am
agreeing to run by the rules of the school and the rules
of the school is that the, you know, the person who's the
principal or the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva has the right to, you
know, impose disciplinary action or has the right to kick me out
if I don't— if I'm not behaving properly.
But you're choosing to go. What?
But I'm still deciding whether— okay, but that's a contractual relationship. So,
you know, if I decide whether to hire you, am I in
a position of authority? Can a גר ger not hire workers because
he could decide to fire them? Right? So that's a very powerful
idea and also the difference about a type of a democratic, you
know, freely entered into types of arrangements, you know, as opposed to—
so maybe like as opposed to a real society in which people
have like, you know, real authority that does not come from those
types of contractual relationships. By the way, so that's interesting because it
points us to the issue of דיין dayan because a דיין dayan
is a case where it's not a contractual relationship. Meaning if you
choose to go to a court of arbitration, right, that's different. But
basically I can give you a summons and compel you to go
to court, that authority is being put on you against your will.
And therefore that would be a real sort of, you know, case
that really would be one of the few cases we have nowadays
that would be that sort of classic type of authority. I just
want to say as a contrast, Young Israel, the Young Israel one
like about 20 years ago or whatever, you know, put out a—
whole story anyway that they were sort of, you know, making whole
statements about their ability to control shul decisions in terms of who
they hire and this and that. And they were speaking about how
they sent out this letter to all their shul presidents how they've
always represented the, you know, the תורה Torah true approach and, you
know, an authentic approach to תורה Torah Judaism. And as an example
of which they said, like for example, the fact that we, you
know, have made it very clear that we cannot that, you know,
that Young Israel shuls— did I say OU? I meant to say
Young Israel. Young Israel, that Young Israel shuls, you know, are not
allowed to have as a president women or גרים geirim because they're
both about a presence of like, you know, positions of authority. So
of course all the presidents read this letter and they say what?
A גר ger can't be a president? So
the whole issue finds that they already had this done or whatever,
but they were so deeply offended when they found that out. Anyway,
so of course for רב משה Rav Moshe that would be a
joke to think that a shul president is a position of authority.
Yes.
To allow a גר ger to be a shul president would violate
the איסור issur of oppressing a גר.
ger. Exactly,
beautifully said, beautifully said. All right, anyway, so— Yes.
On a more serious note, רב משה Rav Moshe's position, might it
have much to do with the Herodian line, most of whom were
converts with non-Jewish mothers, because that was a contractual relationship with the
Romans?
No,
that doesn't matter. It might be a relationship with the Romans, but
it's not a contractual relationship over the people that they have authority
over. Those are the people on whom it's being imposed. So for
רב משה Rav Moshe it's very much about imposed authority over the
people that are the subject, you know, that are subject to that
authority.
Okay, it's a fact that most presidents of Young Israel shuls are
descendants of Herod.
All right, so moving on. Okay, so moving on, so shh, all
right. So says, so therefore, being a דיין dayan is the reason
why גר ger's excluded because that is genuinely a position of imposed
authority. But, he says, that's מקרב אחיך תשים עליך מלך. mikerav acheicha
tasim alecha melech. So he says עליך. alecha. עליך alecha is when
we require מקרב אחיך. mikerav acheicha. If it's over you, a naturally
born Jew, that's when the position and authority, the person holding that
position of authority also has to be a naturally born Jew. אבל
גר דן את חבירו גר, aval ger dan es chaveiro ger, but
if it's not עליך, alecha, if the whole authority is over— another
גר, geir, that would not be a problem. Okay, ואם היתה אמו
מישראל דן אפילו ישראל. v'im hayesa imo miyisrael dan afilu Yisrael.
Now
if his mother was from Jewish stock, then he can judge even
ישראל. Yisrael. Now the funny thing is, of course like our response
to this is like, Of course! What do you mean? That he's
Jewish, he's not a גר. geir. So this is again a funny
thing that the גמרא Gemara sometimes refers, right, to somebody who has
a Jewish mother and not a Jewish father, and not even not
a Jewish father, maybe a father who's a גר, geir, right, a
naturally born Jewish mother and a father who's a גר, geir, like
you know, sees that person in maybe like a quasi-גר geir status,
we you know, not necessarily the way we do, like we have
a very binary sort of system or whatever, non-Jew, גר, geir, naturally
born Jew, right, you know, so whereas the גמרא Gemara there's like
a whole continuum there. So somebody who has a Jewish mother but
a non-Jewish or even a convert father is maybe a little bit
of a question. So we have to insist that that is a
fully מקרב אחיך m'kerev achecha and that person can be a דיין.
dayan. Okay, so it's- but the point is it was a הוה
אמינא hava amina otherwise. אפילו ישראל, afilu Yisrael, that's as a general
rule that that person can be a דיין. dayan. But here's an
interesting point: ולעניין חליצה, u'le'inyan chalitza, but when it comes to who
can be a דיין dayan for חליצה, chalitza, עד שאביו ואמו מישראל.
ad she'aviv v'imo miyisrael. He has to not only himself not be
a גר, geir, his parents have to not be גרים, geirim, not
only his mother even his father, and not only- the implication being
that not only his father can't be a non-Jew, his father can't
even be a גר. geir. Okay, so- so both have to be
completely from genetically Jewish stock. עד שאביו ואמו מישראל שנאמר ונקרא שמו
בישראל. ad she'aviv v'imo miyisrael shene'emar v'nikra shemo b'yisrael. The extra בישראל
b'yisrael here is emphasizing not just the normal requirements of a בית
דין, beis din, but actually the idea that it have to be,
you know, only, you know, a- a naturally born Jew and not
a גר, geir, but an extra element of ישראל. Yisrael. So therefore
completely from, you know, full Jewish stock. So that is a fascinating
הלכה halacha that a special demand by- by גר- geir by חליצה.
chalitza. I want to point out a few issues before we move
on to- because now we're about to leave the גר geir thing,
and there's obviously a huge subject. So few things. Number one, if
you look at the bottom of תוספות Tosfos מרנא דשרא אפומיה, Marana
d'shara apumei, he asks an interesting question. He says first of all-
you know what, let me- let me not read the תוספות, Tosfos,
it'll confuse us, but let me make two points. Number one, once
we have this additional requirement מישראל, miyisrael, presumably that is a requirement
even if the person doing חליצה chalitza's a גר. geir. Right? That
that's a requirement because- one minute, because there's- you know, normally the
requirement of- right, normally we'd say well a גר geir can be
on a בית דין beis din over a גר, geir, okay, but
here there's a special demand of מישראל, miyisrael, it's not just the
פסוק pasuk of שום תשים עליך, som tasim alecha, presumably for חליצה
chalitza that wouldn't be true and you would always need a full
בית דין beis din of ישראל Yisrael even if the person who
was in front of you was a גר. geir. Now the interesting
thing is תוספות Tosfos points out that- that
you might never have a case of that. Why? Because how could
a גר geir have a paternal brother doing ייבום? yibum? So the
only case you could have of a גר geir in the חליצה
chalitza scenario is children of a גר, geir, right? A גר- geir
a man converts, he has two sons, and one of them marries
whatever dies and the other one whatever, children of a גר. geir.
So it's- so that would be already if it's
אמו מישראל והורתו ולידתו בקדושה, imo miyisrael v'horaso v'lidaso bikdusha, that would
be ישראל, Yisrael, it wouldn't be גר. geir. So you don't- so
even the scenario of a גר geir being דן dan over גר
חבירו geir chaveiro doesn't exactly occur in the חליצה chalitza case. That's
just one little fascinating parenthetical point. But the other interesting issue is
the idea that some- that why is it that, you know, we
would have this- normally when do we-
is this an issue that's ever recurring that like that somebody who
is born from Jewish parents somehow is not seen of as, you
know, as a full Jewish status, maybe that's not a fair way
of putting it, but somehow is seen as somehow some possibly excluded
by a phrase like ישראל Yisrael and so on if, you know,
if his parents weren't naturally born Jews. You know, is this something
that we ever hear elsewhere is this just something we have by
חליצה? chalitza? So תוספות Tosfos makes a point of saying that this
is really a very special exception in this חליצה chalitza case. Number
one the example I just gave you, that children of a גר
geir and doing חליצה chalitza with one another, you know, that would
be considered ישראל. Yisrael. And in terms of the הלכה halacha of
שום תשים עליך som tasim alecha etc. right, that is considered- they're
considered ישראל Yisrael completely. And תוספות Tosfos quotes, if you look at
the beginning of this תוספות Tosfos לעניין חליצה עד שאביו ואמו מישראל,
le'inyan chalitza ad she'aviv v'imo miyisrael, he- a few lines in he
says where there's a little ב beis in parentheses like a few
lines into that תוספות, Tosfos, beginning of a line, he says הקשה
ר"י דבפרק נערה בכתובות אמר גבי נערה המאורסה, hiksha Ri d'veperek Na'ara
b'Kesuvos amar gabi na'ara hame'orasa, right,
this betrothed young woman who
committed adultery, שעשתה נבלה בישראל, she'asna nevala b'yisrael, and the גמרא Gemara
says Oh well that would exclude if she was let's say a
convert, a גיורת. giyores. Again the same idea בישראל b'yisrael etc. But
the גמרא Gemara does say that if it's a case of הורתו
ולידתו בקדושה, horaso v'lidaso bikdusha,
that her mother converted but she was born after her mother converted...
It’s not, her mother is not אמו מישראל, imo miYisrael, her אמו
imo is a גר, ger, not this אמו מישראל imo miYisrael category,
nevertheless the גמרא Gemara says ישראל מאיא היא? Yisrael m’aya hi?
She would not be excluded by the word ישראל Yisrael as long
as her mother is Jewish, even if her mother is just Jewish
through conversion, the child is considered totally מישראל. miYisrael. Okay, so the
basic point I want you to see from that is that, you
know, that basically כל התורה כולה, kol HaTorah kulla, if somebody’s mother
is Jewish or even mother’s a convert, then whether the father is
a convert, is not a convert, is this or that or whatever,
you know, that’s sort of our general approach. The person is totally
considered ישראל, Yisrael, not considered even a גר, ger, etc., for whatever
הלכות halakhot might be different for a גר. ger. That is 100%
the rule. This case is a very rare exception to that rule
and says that to be on the בית דין beit din by
חליצה, chalitzah, it’s not enough that not only can the person not
be a גר, ger, but the parents can’t be גרים. gerim. They
have to be actually completely, you know, natural Jewish stock.
So why is there a difference?
So that’s what תוספות Tosafot asks, and then he figures it out
because we have an extra פסוק pasuk here, whatever תוספות Tosafot works
that through. Okay, that’s number one in terms of this demand here
of
אביו ואמו מישראל, aviv v’imo miYisrael, this very special demand. The other
thing to be aware of in terms of the question about גר
דן את חבירו ger dan et chaveiro and where is this or
not allowed is two points. Number one is תוספות Tosafot makes the
point that if the people, as I said before going back to
the רב משה, Rav Moshe, enter into an arbitration agreement, meaning basically
choose to say, why don’t you Mr. גר, Ger, why don’t you
become
our דיין? dayan? We’re going to sort of, as opposed to a
compelled case, but a case of actually, you know, a פשרה psharah
or some type of a choosing
of the authority, freely accepting the authority,
then a גר ger can be
on a בית דין. beit din. Even
though the decision is binding, and that really is like sort of
now that I gave you the רב משה, Rav Moshe, that should
be relatively obvious. Okay, that’s point number one. Point number two is:
what about when a גר ger is excluded from a בית דין,
beit din, what type of בית דין beit din is he excluded
from? So take a look at רש"י Rashi here, גר דן את
חבירו, ger dan et chaveiro, the top רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi says
the following: דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot,
the exclusion is only for a capital crime, presumably also let’s say
lashes. אבל דיני ממונות אפילו כל ישראל דתנן הכל כשרים לדון דיני
ממונות רמינא לה הכל לאתויי גר. aval dinei mamonot afilu kol Yisrael
d’tenan hakol kesherim la-don dinei mamonot raminah lah hakol l’atuyei ger.
Okay,
so according to רש"י, Rashi, and again you understand if it’s an
idea of imposed authority, sure you can have imposed authority with money
as well, but the much greater sense of power is when it’s
about something to do something to you personally, to give you lashes,
to execute you and so on. Okay, so that’s what the גר
ger is excluded from,
only this גר דן את חבירו, ger dan et chaveiro, meaning he’s
not excluded, meaning he can be דן dan את חבירו דיני נפשות.
et chaveiro dinei nefashot. When he’s excluded from being דן dan a
non-גר, ger, it’s only in the דיני נפשות dinei nefashot category. תוספות
Tosafot disagrees. תוספות Tosafot says גר דן את חבירו דבר תורה פירש
בקונטרס היינו לדיני נפשות, ger dan et chaveiro devar Torah peireish b'kuntres
haynu l'dinei nefashot,
and he doesn’t repeat his whole discussion, but elsewhere in ש"ס, Shas,
תוספות Tosafot has a long discussion and says no, a גר ger
is excluded even from a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot בית דין beit
din over ישראל. Yisrael. So important debate of רש"י תוספות. Rashi Tosafot.
So again to summarize: a גר ger can דן גר חבירו. dan
ger chaveiro. A גר ger cannot דן dan a naturally born ישראל.
Yisrael. Which type of a בית דין beit din is he excluded
from? According to רש"י, Rashi, only a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot one,
that’s one of real authority, of real power. תוספות Tosafot says even
a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot one. But both agree that even תוספות
Tosafot says even a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot he’s excluded, תוספות Tosafot
would say but if they were freely entering in and accepting that
authority upon themselves, the parties, that would be okay. That would not
be imposed authority. And then the special case by
חליצה, chalitzah, that there you need not only somebody not a גר,
ger, but אמו ואביו מישראל. imo v’aviv miYisrael.
Yes, דיין dayan and he is דינא דמלכותא דינא dina d’malchuta dina
binding in a non-Jewish court, right?
What do you mean?
In the Middle Ages, the non-Jewish courts had given autonomy to the
Jewish courts and the Jewish courts had power. Right.
Nowadays, if you choose.
Right, so the question, yes, so nowadays any going in America to
a בית דין beit din is a case of accepting authority upon
yourself, not imposed authority. Right. The question is in Israel, it would
be different, right? I don’t know again how does it work in
Israel, like if I want to sue you and I want to
bring you to a בית דין beit din and you want to
go to a בית משפט, beit mishpat, right? I know like by
some marriage cases, particularly by divorce, it’s whoever gets there first. So,
you know, whoever files first gets to determine the venue, whether it’s
בית דין beit din or a בית משפט, beit mishpat, which creates
a very interesting dynamic because women’s interests are much more protected as
a rule in the בית משפט beit mishpat over the בית דין,
beit din, so therefore if it looks like there’s going to be
a divorce, it’s a race to
who’s going to file. But I don't know how it works in
a דיני ממונות Dinei Mamonos case about who gets to decide the
venue. Maybe it's the same thing. You know, yeah, Charlie?
In Ontario, Canada, the בית דין Beis Din
don't even have the ability to have their decisions enforced.
Like it can't be a binding arbitration panel?
Not for religious courts.
But if they don't identify as a religious court, but somebody just
says these three people are binding arbitration and happens to name three
rabbis?
If they follow religious law, they are not enforced. This was a
law that was passed about ten years ago to kick Sharia courts
out of business. And we were the collateral damage.
Really, fascinating. Okay, yeah?
Does that line of thinking about if we choose to put somebody
in that position of authority come into conflict with the idea about
the king and say that the king is put into authority?
That's a good point, right? Because when the initial institution of a
king was established, it was שום תשים עליך מלך, som tashim alecha
melech, it was coming through the people demanding it. But once the
institution was there, they were no longer voting on their king, you
know. So, and also the king's authority is much greater, right? It's
much more unilateral and life and death and so on and so
forth. Right. But that's, right. Right, meaning that's the question too. Right,
meaning, so that's a good point, and this came up in Israel
in terms of having women, appointing women to like, many many years
ago, I mean when it was Rav Kook the question was could
women vote? You know, then afterwards the question was could women be
appointed to these, what do they call them, these religious councils? Is
that positions of authority? Right, so there as well that's a really
like elected position. Once you're in that position, yes, you've got power
and so on, but it's a, the people who are electing somebody
and freely accepting that person to say, "Yeah, but I didn't vote
for her, so she can't have authority over me." You know, but
then you're part of a whole system and so on. So it's
fascinating how this stuff then gets translated into democratic realities. Okay, let's
move on and representational authority. Okay, so now the Gemara says like
this: אמר רבא אמר רב כהנא אמר רב. Amar Rava amar Rav
Kahana amar Rav. So that was fascinating few lines about ger, back
to
Chalitzah. אמר רב, Amar Rav, אם יבוא אליהו ויאמר, im yavo Eliyahu
ve-yomar, if Eliyahu HaNavi would come and say, חולצין במנעל, choltzin be-minal,
that you're allowed to do Chalitzah with a shoe as opposed to
a sandal, שומעין לו, shomin lo, you'd listen to him. אין חולצין
בסנדל, ein choltzin be-sandal, if he would say you can't do Chalitzah
with a sandal, אין שומעין לו, ein shomin lo, you would not
listen to him,
שכבר נהגו העם בסנדל, she-kevar nahagu ha-am be-sandal, the practice has been
established to use a sandal. ורב יוסף אמר רב
כהנא אמר רב,
Ve-Rav
Yosef
amar Rav Kahana amar Rav, אם יבוא אליהו ויאמר אין חולצין במנעל
שומעין לו. im yavo Eliyahu ve-yomar ein choltzin be-minal shomin lo. Almost
similar but he says if he were to tell me you can't
use a shoe, then you would listen, as opposed to if he
told me you could use a shoe. What obviously this reflects is
that as a general rule they weren't using a shoe, right? So
they didn't have an established practice that you use a shoe. The
established practice was you use a sandal. So therefore, since we don't
have an established practice of using a shoe or not, we would
listen to which way Eliyahu would tell us to go about a
shoe. Okay, but, but if he were to say אין חולצין בסנדל,
ein choltzin be-sandal, if he'd say you can't use a sandal, אין
שומעין לו, ein shomin lo, you would not listen to him, שכבר
נהגו העם בסנדל, she-kevar nahagu ha-am be-sandal, because the people have already
established the practice of using a sandal. So מאי בינייהו, mai beineihu,
what difference is reflected? One of them says if he would have
told me you could use a shoe, the other says if he
told me you couldn't use a shoe. So איכא בינייהו מנעל לכתחילה,
ika beineihu minal le-chat-chila, whether לכתחילה le-chat-chila you're allowed to use a
shoe. One of them assumes that לכתחילה, le-chat-chila, right, you don't use
a shoe, so what would Eliyahu tell me that would be a
חידוש? chiddush? He'd tell me לכתחילה le-chat-chila you could. And the other
one assumes לכתחילה le-chat-chila you could use a shoe, so what would
Eliyahu tell me is a חידוש, chiddush, the חידוש chiddush that Eliyahu
might tell me is is that לכתחילה le-chat-chila you can't. So it's
all anyway but now it's basically an argument on paper because in
practice we use a sandal and that we won't listen to Eliyahu.
But in terms of in theory, what do we hold? I might
hold in theory that a shoe is לכתחילה, le-chat-chila, I'd listen to
Eliyahu if he said בדיעבד. bedieved. I might hold in theory a
shoe is בדיעבד, bedieved, I'd listen to Eliyahu if he said לכתחילה.
le-chat-chila. Now this is a fascinating, potentially fascinating theological discussion here. And
the Gemara is going to completely ignore it and just go on
to discussing shoes and sandals. So, but yes, it's part of the
general sort of theme of, you know, לא בשמים היא, lo bashamayim
hi, and what's I think but what's fascinating about it is it
doesn't make as bold claims as a classic לא בשמים היא lo
bashamayim hi claim would be. A classic לא בשמים היא lo bashamayim
hi claim would be אין שומעין לו ein shomin lo even if
he told me something different about the מנהג. minhag. Right, meaning this
is really making a statement about the power of established practice, right?
That's what it's saying. I won't listen to Eliyahu because practice, you
cannot say a הלכה halakha that complete that undermines what has been
established as the practice, which is an amazing statement about the weight
of practice in הלכה, halakha, right? Because, you know, so much we
assume that the authority is in the text and in the Gemara
and so on. I just gave a talk on this in the
yeshiva earlier this week that, yeah, for the בעלי התוספות Baalei HaTosafot
in particular, what the people are practicing, you know, has an enormous
weight in assuming what the הלכה halakha is, and if there's a
problem with the text, you'll figure out how to make the text
work. The text is like Eliyahu as it were, not exactly, but
the point is the power of this statement is how powerful established
practice is. If you really want to make a more powerful statement
of לא בשמים היא, lo bashamayim hi, then you would say you
don't listen to Eliyahu even about the מנהג. minhag. Who cares what
Eliyahu says? You know, is he an אמורא? Amora? Is he a
תנא? Tanna? If he's an אמורא, Amora, if he's a תנא, Tanna,
if he has a voice and he wants to be one of
the rabbis and he wants to discuss it and debate it, we'll
debate it. But we wouldn't give any de facto deference to him
about any הלכה, Halacha, right, whether it's practice or not practice הלכה,
Halacha, since what does it give even a נביא? Navi? נביא Navi
doesn't have status in a הלכה Halachic debate. So I'm serious, the
stronger statement should be אין שומעין לו Ein Shomin Lo even by
the מנהג. Minhag. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara here, it does not
make as extreme of a statement of לא בשמים היא, Lo Bashamayim
Hi, it actually makes a more powerful statement as opposed to the
power of מנהג Minhag and practice, and that's important because then you'll
have, as I said, cases what's not practice against a voice of
heaven, but it's a practice against a text, against the גמרא, Gemara,
and that statements like this that give weight to practice are very
significant. Yes.
But there's a mitigating factor here. This is endorsed practice because we've
already approved נהגו עם Nahagu Am but they've already adopted it.
Right, that's a good point. That's a good point. It is a
practice that the rabbis are overseeing, so it's been it's sort of
a rabbinic position that's reinforced by practice. So that's a very good
point.
Like we saw last night and I was
trying to work out, yeah, what is it? Right, exactly, exactly. You
know, and it raises questions about when people are practicing and they're
in a frum community and there are rabbis that are present and
not saying anything and not opposing it, like is that also considered
as like as approved of
practice? The implicit silence. But you're right, this is that is an
important point to make that this is a type of practice that's
not only implicitly accepted, but people would go to חליצה Chalitza in
בית דין. Beit Din. So it would be exactly like a
rabbinic rabbinically established practice. So that is a very important point. That
is correct.
Standard דברי רבנן Divrei Rabbanan on the continuum, right?
Right. Okay, so that's a lot of very fascinating גמרא. Gemaras. Now
we get back to sandals and shoes. So let's take a look.
Okay. So גמרא Gemara says like this. ואתנן, Ve-atnan,
so the גמרא Gemara says ולמאן דאמר U-le-man De-amar even לכתחילה, Lechatchila,
according to the מן דאמר Man De-amar that says you can use
a shoe even לכתחילה, Lechatchila, we'll see what the possible problem of
a shoe would be. But let's at least now just look at
the facts. One that says you could use a shoe even לכתחילה
Lechatchila ואתנן, Ve-atnan, don't we learn in our משנה Mishnah חלצה במנעל
חליצתה כשירה, Chaltza Be-min'al Chalitzatah Kesherah, that if you used a shoe
it is good? But the language is if, like בדיעבד Bedi'avad it's
good. בדיעבד Bedi'avad לכתחילה Lechatchila לא, Lo, only בדיעבד. Bedi'avad. So גמרא
Gemara says no, הוא הדין אפילו לכתחילה, Hu Ha-din Afillu Lechatchila, no
even לכתחילה Lechatchila would be fine. ואיידי דבעי למיתני סיפא באנפליא חליצתה
פסולה, Ve-aidi De-ba'ei Le-mitni Seifa Be-anpalya Chalitzatah Pesulah,
since in the end it's going to say that if you use
like a sock or a slipper, it's invalid אפילו בדיעבד, Afillu Bedi'avad,
that there the invalidity is even a בדיעבד Bedi'avad invalidity post-facto תני
נמי רישא בדיעבד, Tana Nami Reisha Bedi'avad,
so the language in the beginning was if you used a מנעל,
Min'al, a shoe, but the real point is you can use a
shoe לכתחילה, Lechatchila, at least according to one opinion. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. ומנעל לכתחילה תנאי היא, U-min'al Lechatchila
Tanna'ei Hi, whether you can use a shoe לכתחילה Lechatchila is a
debate of תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא, De-tanya, it's taught in a ברייתא Baraita
אמר רבי יוסי Amar Rabbi Yosi פעם אחת הלכתי לנציבין, Pa'am Achat
Halachti Li-netzivin, one time I went to the place Netzivin ומצאתי זקן
אחד U-matzati Zaken Echad and I saw an old man. אמרתי לו,
Amarti Lo, I said to him, כלום אתה בקי ברבי יהודה בן
בתירה? Kelum Atah Baki Be-Rabbi Yehuda Ben Beteira? Are you do you
know Rabbi Yehuda Ben Beteira who was from Netzivin? אמר לי הין,
Amar Li Hein, yes על שולחני הוא תדיר, Al Shulchani Hu Tadir,
he always comes to my house for Shabbos, he's a regular guest.
So then he said to him, okay, כלום ראית שחלץ ביבמה? Kelum
Ra'ita She-chalatz Be-yevamah? Have you ever seen him do a חליצה Chalitza
with a sister-in-law? אמר לי ראיתי שחלץ הרבה פעמים, Amar Li Ra'iti
She-chalatz Harbeh Fe'amim, so yeah, actually I saw many times. I don't
know if it was over the during the table and during the
meal, but okay. Yeah, I know I actually I've witnessed it many
times him doing חליצה. Chalitza. That a sister-in-law did her חליצה. Chalitza.
במנעל או בסנדל? Bi-min'al O Be-sandal? Did he use a shoe or
did he use a sandal? אמר לי, Amar Li, he said to
me, וכי חולצין במנעל? Ve-chi Choltzin Bi-min'al? Why, do you think you
can use a shoe? So I guess that was an answer. Okay,
now everybody takes out the next few words which makes it sound
like it's דאורייתא De-oraita which is not in the תוספתא Tosefta and
it's not in the assumption of the גמרא. Gemara.
So he just sort of was like shocked, of
course what do you mean a shoe? You think he can use
a shoe? No, of course he always uses the sandal. אמרתי לו,
Amarti Lo, I said to him, אם כן, Im Ken, if that's
true that it's so like not even in the פרשה, Parashah, not
even to be thought of that you could use a shoe, מה
ראה רבי מאיר לומר חלצה במנעל חליצתה כשירה? Mah Ra'ah Rabbi Meir
Lomar Chaltza Bi-min'al Chalitzatah Kesherah? I wonder what motivated Rabbi Meir to
say, right, Rabbi Meir Rabbi Yehuda's sort of counterpart, I wonder what
motivated Rabbi Meir to say בדיעבד Bedi'avad it was good. Of course
the funny thing is Rabbi Yehuda never said בדיעבד Bedi'avad it wasn't
good, he just never would have done it לכתחילה, Lechatchila, never would
have done it. He's not saying that בדיעבד Bedi'avad it's not good.
Okay, רבי יעקב אומר משמיה דרבי מאיר, Rabbi Yaakov Omer Mishmeih De-Rabbi
Meir, Rabbi Yaakov said in the name of Rabbi Meir חולצין במנעל
לכתחילה, Choltzin Bi-min'al Lechatchila, you can even do it לכתחילה. Lechatchila. Now
the גמרא Gemara wants to understand what would be the לכתחילה Lechatchila
problem. ומאן דאמר לכתחילה לא, U-man De-amar Lechatchila Lo, according to the
approach that לכתחילה Lechatchila you can't do it מאי טעמא, Mai Ta'ama,
why not? אילימא משום דהוי פנצא מעל וערקסה מעל דמעל, Ilima Mishum
De-havei Pantza Mei-al Ve-arkasa Mei-al De-mei-al, if it's because you have basically
like the tongue or like the leather of the shoe is the
one that's directly on the foot and the string is on the
on. right it says וחלצה נעלו מעל רגלו. v'chaltzah na'alo mei'al raglo.
So if you undo a shoe, what do you have to do?
You have to undo the laces first and then you remove the
leather part shoe, you know, the actual physical shoe that's on the
leg, you remove it. So there's two things that are on top,
there's laces on top of the tongue and of the sort of,
you know, the the whole leather upper of the shoe, that's what's
called the upper, the, no, what's that thing called? I mean the
whole top, the whole shoe part, is that the upper? Okay, so
you have all of that has to be two things have to,
you know, are layered on top of our shoes are layered on
top of the foot. So that's the problem. The ערקסא arkasa of
the string is מעל דמעל mei'al de-mei'al above the thing that's on
the shoe. והתורה אמרה מעל, ve-ha-Torah amrah mei'al, remove it from on
top of his foot, ולא מעל דמעל, ve-lo mei'al de-mei'al, and not
from something on top of on top of. He's just undoing a
lace. I know, but okay, maybe that's part of the problem that
there are two things that are on top of the foot as
it were. אי הכי אפילו דיעבד נמי לא. ei hachi afilu di-avad
nami lo. So if that's true, okay, theoretically that's the possible position,
maybe that was Rabbi Yehuda's thought if Rabbi Yehuda actually
thought it wasn't
good בדיעבד, di-avad, but but that would not that then it would
really be a בדיעבד di-avad problem. We're saying it's only at most
a לכתחילה l'chatchila problem.
So the Gemara says fine, you're right, it's not that problem. גזירה,
gezeirah, it's a safeguard משום מנעל מרופט. mishum minal merupat.
We're afraid about a type of a like of of of a
torn shoe, okay, a broken and a torn shoe, so which would
not be כשר kosher בדיעבד. di-avad. So you don't have to worry
about a broken sandal. Why do you not have to worry about
somebody wearing a broken sandal?
Because you can't wear it.
But if you've got a shoe, right, that's like got tears and
broken etc. because it's got all this structural covering and support, it's
still possible to get it and keep it on your foot. So
it could be broken to a point that הלכתית halachit it's no
longer a shoe, but you're still wearing it. So because we want
to avoid those cases, we want to just avoid shoes altogether. אינמי
משום חצי מנעל ei nami mishum chatzi minal which is a variation
of the idea, half of a shoe. Okay, אמר רב, amar Rav,
אילמלא דחזיתיה לחביבי דחלץ בסנדל דאית ליה שנצין, ilmalei de-chaziteih le-chavivi de-chalatz
be-sandal de-it lei shnitzin,
had I not seen my beloved, which is Rabbi Chiya, who did
a חליצה chalitzah with a sandal that has שנצין shnitzin which are
basically like straps, אמינא לא הוי חליצה אלא בסנדל דטייא דמהדק טפי.
aminah lo havei chalitzah
ella be-sandal de-taya de-mehadak tefei.
I would have only used the sandal of like of a
nomad's that is even tighter, okay, somehow that as opposed to some
type of I don't know like a winding strap that doesn't get
really tightened, I would have used, I again I don't know the
sandals, but I would have used something that was much more tighter
on the foot. Okay,
why exactly he would think that that's better, maybe it's more of
an idea of removing, if it's on better then it's more of
an act of removing when you remove it. והא, ve-ha, I don't
know if your footnotes there in your Steinsaltz or whatever say anything
about what it looks like and why it's different. Charlie, I see
you got some pictures. I can't see from this distance.
Just nomadic, it's tighter on the foot.
Oh, you mean just because they walk in the desert or whatever
and they don't walk around in a nice paved city, they need
tighter shoes. Okay, does it describe how they're tighter?
No, it's actually just a couple of but it's got some nice
pictures though.
Okay, fine, anyway, all right, והאי דידן ve-hai didan and the one
that we use אף על גב דאית בה קטרא
קטרינן בה. af al gav de-it beh kitra katrinan beh. Okay, and
ours even though okay even though it's got like a knot okay
and you you know you make like a knot and that keeps
it on nevertheless קטרינן בה מסני. katrinan beh masni. We still like
tie it with what do you call it
with straps like we wrap around straps as well we don't just
use a knot to keep it on. כי היכי דתהוי חליצה מעליא.
ki heichi de-tehavi chalitzah me-alya. Again if it's on if it's on
tighter then the act of removing is a better act of removing
so you know you could keep something on by making a simple
knot right you you know without without wrapping things around but a
simple knot will keep it on but won't make it tight. So
we want to דוקא davka use things that have straps to not
just keep it on but keep it on nice and tight so
it's a good חליצה. chalitzah. Once we started getting all these requirements
of a sandal with straps that's wrapped that's tight that's this that's
that you start you know developing these חליצה chalitzah shoes that then
you know that we have that we use you know when we
have to do a חליצה. chalitzah. Okay so now the Gemara says
like this. Okay אמר רב יהודה אמר רב amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav הותרת יבמה לשוק בשמיטת
רוב העקב. hotarat yevamah la-shuk bi-shmitat rov ha-akev.
Now we've got what the shoe is and shoe's got to be
on tight how you how you remove the shoe. It says it's
enough that you remove the majority of the heel. You know once
the heel sort of gets out of the whole straps gets you
know you know imagine taking off your shoe right once you take
off the heel part even though you haven't slipped off the top
of the shoe that's considered to be removed okay the majority of
the heel. מיתיבי meitivei I ask you on this הותרו רצועות מנעל
hutru retzuot minal here cases where it's not going to be good
if the straps undid themselves the woman didn't undo them ומנעל וסנדל
u-minal ve-sandal או ששמט רוב הרגל o she-shamat rov ha-regel
or that most of the leg had slipped out by itself, not
by him. that the woman had done it, חליצתה פסולה, chalitzatah psulah,
then the חליצה chalitzah is invalid. Okay? טעמא דשמט הוא, Ta'ama deshmat
hu, the reason is because he removed his leg, the woman didn't
do it. But okay, or he did, right. The first case was
that it just did it by itself, the second is he removed
most of his leg. So the reason is that he removed most
of his leg. השמטה היא, Hashamta hi, if she had removed most
of his
leg, חליצתה כשרה, chalitzatah ksheirah, it would be kosher. So the point
is it's emphasizing here leg and not heel. רוב הרגל Rov ha-regel
in, the majority of the leg yes, רוב העקב rov ha-akeiv no,
not the majority of the heel. Now again, it's a little confusing
because sometimes the Gemara by leg mean leg or does the Gemara
by leg mean foot? Actually I'm curious, how do your English translates
this? Does it say leg or foot? Foot. Foot. You have? Okay,
foot.
Well, it says, השמטה היא, Hashamta hi, where was, you know, most
of the foot, then רוב הרגל rov ha-regel they say here also
foot.
Foot. Yeah, foot. Okay, anyway, so it could be foot. So anyway,
so is it about the foot and not the heel? So therefore
it would be sort of saying that you, it's not enough to
remove the majority of the heel. You have to also remove the
majority of the foot, right? If you think about again taking off
your shoes, it's not enough to get it off the heel part,
you have to get it off most of the foot. If it's
about a leg, you know, maybe it's talking about the straps, and
therefore maybe it's getting the leg out of the straps, and that
could maybe even happen if you get the leg out of the
straps before you get it removed from the heel. But let's assume
that leg means here foot, okay, so look, you need the whole
foot, you need the majority of the foot, not just the majority
of the heel. So the Gemara says, רוב הרגל rov ha-regel in,
רוב העקב rov ha-akeiv no. So the Gemara says, לא היינו רוב
הרגל היינו רוב העקב. Lo, hainu rov ha-regel hainu rov ha-akeiv. When
we say the majority of the foot we mean the heel. Okay.
ואמאי קרי ליה רוב הרגל V'amai kari leh rov ha-regel? So why
do they call it the foot? דכולא חילא דכרעא אלידיה דחיס D'kula
cheila d'char'a a-leideh dachis because the whole weight of the leg rests
on the heel. So therefore yes, you know, that's why, I mean
that's explaining why the position we're saying heel counts, because that's basically
where the weight of the leg rests. I mean I guess you
could have said it's not about the weight of the leg, right?
It's about what keeps the shoe on. What keeps the shoe on
is that it's over the heel, right? When it's over the top
of the foot it doesn't stay on so well, right? You could
have said that. But the Gemara's saying no, we're defining heel as
important because the heel is supporting the weight of the leg and
the weight of the body. And therefore we're really defining the heel
as the foot. So when we say majority of the foot we
mean majority of the heel. Okay. So now the Gemara says like
this: מסייע ליה לרב ינאי. Mesayei leh l'Rav Yannai. This supports Rav
Yannai. דאמר רב ינאי, D'amar Rav Yannai, בין שהתיר הוא ושמטה היא,
bein she-hitir hu v'shamatah hi, whether, now this thing that said that
it's a problem if the straps undo themselves or he removes or
he gets his foot out of the shoe, indicates that she has
to do two things. She has to both undo the straps and
remove his leg. So that idea, that implication supports Rav Yannai. Okay,
cause this is what Rav Yannai says, בין שהתיר הוא ושמטה היא,
bein she-hitir hu v'shamatah hi, if he undid the straps and she
took the shoe off, בין שהתירה היא ושמט הוא, bein she-hitirah hi
v'shamat hu, or she undid the straps and he took the shoe
off, חליצתה פסולה, chalitzatah psulah, it's invalid, עד שתתיר היא ותשמוט היא.
ad she-tatir hi v'tishmot hi. She has to both undo the straps
and remove the shoe. בעי רב ינאי, Ba'ei Rav Yannai, now Rav
Yannai asked: קרעתהו מהו Kera'atehu mahu?
Let's say she did not take off the shoe by maintaining keeping
the shoe whole and slipping it off, but she got the shoe
off his foot by ripping it off, by like basically like taking
a knife and cutting it off of his foot. Cutting it off
of his foot. Okay, what would be the story there? So שרפתהו
מהו Sraftehu mahu? Let's say she burned it off of his foot.
Okay. Without burning his foot? I don't know if she did or
didn't burn his foot, but that's not our halachic question. Okay. גילוי
כרעא בעינן ואיכא Gilui kar'a ba'inan v'ika?
Does she just have to expose his foot? או דלמא חליצה בעינן
וליכא O dilma chalitzah ba'inan v'leika? Or maybe חליצה chalitzah is specifically
what the Torah says, וחלצה, v'chaltzah, but is the point of the
Torah a specific act of removal? And removal is defined as maintaining
the thing whole and taking it off? Or is it just saying
get it, get it off, get to the end result? It's a
classic Brisk חקירה, chakira, right? Is it about achieving the end result
an exposed foot, or is it about the act and the act
of חליצה chalitzah defined in a particular way? Right? Because you could
ask a question, let's say the Gemara, let's say it didn't get
straps. The Gemara wasn't explicit that it needed straps, it was a
little bit unclear on that part, but the Gemara did sound like
in theory you could just have a knot, right? It says you
know, we prefer to have straps because it's
tighter, you know, but anyway, so you know, when we said she
has to undo the straps and it, is that because there's an
idea part of the act of חליצה chalitzah is undoing straps? Or
is it just no, that's what you need to do in order
to get the shoe off? And she's got to do all parts
of getting the shoe off. Okay, so this is the question. Is
it basically about achieving the end result, or is it a formal
process of removing the shoe even if the end result is achieved?
And then we could identify maybe that requires straps, maybe that requires
this. What is part of that process of removing the shoe?
Yes. Just like to raise the idea about, she's almost, this is
not the only, we also find the idea of giving over the
shoe in Ruth, right? It was just a financial transaction. So if
we look at that by analogy, this is some kind of a
transactional situation where he's being granted his freedom
from the
obligation of yibum.
Right. Right. So that's a good point. I mean, that's a very
important question about comparing this whole thing to the Ruth story, you
know, because I mean Ruth sort of has a whole mixing up
of, like, you know, the act of יבום yibbum and the act
of גאולה ge'ulah and, you know, and is that what's going on
there? A type of חליפין chalipin or a type of חליצה? chalitzah?
So, you know, it's complicated to sort of make that comparison because,
you know, because the because there are different what we know of
as different הלכה halakhic categories, what even the תורה Torah seems to
identify as different categories. Right? There's the גאולה ge'ulah and then there's
the חליצה, chalitzah, you know, and they all sort of get a
bit intertwined there. What?
Exactly. That is what
it does say.
You know, that what's the פסוק? pasuk? וזאת לפנים בישראל, Vezot le-fanim
be-Yisrael, like, על הגאולה ועל התמורה
לקיים כל דבר,
al ha-ge'ulah ve-al ha-temurah
le-kayem kol davar, which is why the גמרא Gemara reads it as
a type of חליצה. chalitzah. So it's interesting, you're right, that at
least that פסוק, pasuk, whatever is exactly going on, but at least
taking that פסוק, pasuk, you know, and saying do does that make
us want to look at this as somehow transactional? Like I am
giving you your freedom type of a thing. It's a good point,
rather than ritualistic. So, okay. Excellent point. So now the גמרא Gemara
continues. What if so what's the story? תיקו. Teiku. We don't know,
we don't know. תיקו, Teiku, אליהו. Eliyahu. Okay. You do realize that
even though your your fifth-grade רבי rebbe told you תיקו Teiku meant
did people have רבנים rebbeim who told them this?
Yeah, yeah, the תשבי Tishbi
Michael
and I
had the same רבי. rebbe. No, not really. תשבי יתרץ קושיות ובעיות,
Tishbi yitaretz kushyot u-be'ayot, right? תשבי, Tishbi, אליהו התשבי Eliyahu HaTishbi will
answer all of our questions, right? So anyway, so that's exactly nice
point, since we mentioned אליהו Eliyahu before. But that's not what תיקו
Teiku means. You know what תיקו Teiku means? תיקום. Teikum. The the
matter remains standing. It stands as a question. We don't have a
resolution. Okay anyway, אליהו Eliyahu has nothing to do with it.
Okay, אליהו'ס Eliyahu's going
to come and tell you? I don't know. בעי מיניה רב נחמיה.
Bai minei Rav Nechemiah. Anyway, that's our question. Fascinating question. Is it
the process of removal or is it achieving the end result? בעי
מיניה רב נחמיה מרבה. Bai minei Rav Nechemiah mi-Rabba. רב נחמיה Rav
Nechemiah asked רבה: Rabba: שני מנעלים זה על גב זה מהו? Shenei
minalayim zeh al gav zeh, mahu?
Let's say a person wears two shoes. So, היכי דמי? heichi dami?
What's the case? אילימא דשלפתה לעילאי וקאי תתאי. Ileima de-shalafti le-ilai ve-kaie
tatayi. מעל אמר רחמנא. Me-al, amar rachmana.
Let's say she just removes the top shoe and the bottom shoe
remained. So, מעל אמר רחמנא, Me-al, amar rachmana, she has to remove
it from the foot. Okay? ולא מעל דמעל, Velo me-al de-me-al, not
from the thing that's above the above, not from the shoe on
top of the shoe. So clearly that wouldn't לא צריכא דקרעתה לעילאי
ושלפתה לתתאי. Lo, tzericha dekarta le-ilai ve-shalafti le-tatayi. Here's what she did:
she tore the top one
and she removed the bottom one. So this whole thing we're describing
before about tearing, let's say she actually did remove the bottom one,
but after tearing off the top one. ושלפתה לתתאי, Ve-shalafti le-tatayi, and
the top וקאי עילאי, ve-kaie ilai, but the top one never left
his foot. Okay? So she didn't tear the top one off, she
exposed it enough, opened it enough that she could get in there
and remove the bottom one, but the top one remained. So she
removed the shoe from his foot while keeping his foot covered. Okay?
It's like sometimes, you know, you take off your undershirt while you
keep your top shirt on or something, a sweater on.
Okay, so right.
וקאי עילאי. ve-kaie ilai. מאי? Mai? חליצה בעינן ואיכא? Chalitzah be'inan ve-ika?
Do we just need the removal? And she did remove it. או
דלמא גילויה דכרעא בעינן וליכא? O dilma gilluya de-khara be'inan ve-leika? It's
an interesting flip of the other case. Right, where before said: what
if she exposed the foot without removing the shoe? Here here it
is: what if you removed the shoe without exposing the foot? Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says: ומי איכא כי האי גוונא? umi ika
ki hai gavna? Would you ever have a case like that? תוספות
Tosafot says what do you mean? We have many more bizarre cases
in the גמרא Gemara than this. But okay, the גמרא Gemara says:
would you ever have a case like that? אין, In, yes, דחזיוה
רבנן לרב יהודה דנפיק בחמשה זוזי de-chazyu rabanan le-Rav Yehuda de-nafik be-chamshah
zuzei or זוגי מוקי zugei muki לשוקא. le-shuka. They saw רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda went out with five slippers or pairs of shoes or
whatever into the marketplace. So sometimes people
wear shoes on top of shoes. Funny question. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav. Said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in
the name of רב: Rav: יבמה שהגדילה בין האחים. Yevamah she-higdia bein
ha-achim. She grew up amongst the brothers. Meaning, here she is, she's
a יבמה yevamah and her husband died, but she's young. So we're
waiting for her to grow up till it's time to do יבום.
yibbum. So she's been spending the last ten years, you know, in
the vicinity and in the household or whatever of the brothers, one
of whom has to do either יבום yibbum or חליצה. chalitzah. ופעם
נפלה U-tefillah naflah to one of the brothers. Once she's of age,
she can go ahead and do יבום. yibbum. The what would be
the concern? ואין חוששין שמא חלצה סנדל לאחד מהם. Ve-ein chosheshin shema
chaltza sandal le-echad me-hem. Interesting little reflection of societal norms. Look, here
she is my younger sister, I come and I sit down after
a long day or my younger sister-in-law, my sister-in-law, and I say:
here honey, help me take off my shoe. Okay, you know, because
there was a whole מלאכה, melachah, right? You had to undo the
strap or whatever. So there I am, I'm sitting on the
couch, you know, my my brother's widow, you know, who's all of
ten years old, is helping me take off my shoe. So she
did a חליצה chalitzah to me!
But she didn't do it
in front of the בית דין. beit din. Okay, so that's an
interesting question, is the are the פסוקים... pesukim... מעכב. me'akev. Is the
spitting מעכב? me'akev? Okay, so we'll worry about that. But that's a
good question too. So anyway, he's saying we're not concerned that maybe
she did that, and then it would have been a חליצה, chalitzah,
and if she would have done a חליצה chalitzah we can't do
יבום yibum anymore. So the גמרא Gemara says, טעמא דלא חזינן. ta'ama
d'lo chazinan. The reason is we didn't see her do it, so
we're not concerned that she did it. הא חזינן, ha chazinan, had
we seen her remove a shoe, חיישינן, chaishinan, we would—that's the גמרא's
Gemara's question, we would be concerned. Is that true? והתניא, ve-hatanya, didn't
we teach in a ברייתא, beraita, בין שנתכוין הוא בלא נתכונה היא,
bein she-nitkaven hu ve-lo nitkavna hi, whether he had intent and she
didn't, או שנתכונה היא בלא נתכוין הוא, o she-nitkavna hi ve-lo nitkaven
hu, or she had intent and he didn't, חליצתה פסולה, chalitzatah psulah,
it's not a חליצה, chalitzah, עד שיתכוונו שניהם, ad she-yitkavnu shneihem, they
both have to have כוונה. kavanah. תוספות Tosafot says, not only is
it both have to have כוונה kavanah in terms of what's going
on in their head, if you take a look at
תוספות, Tosafot, דקתני תנא ברייתא, de-katani tana beraita, תוספות Tosafot says,
ומדקתני, u-mi-de-katani, you see
the תוספות Tosafot right there, ומדקתני עד שיתכוונו שניהם כאחד, u-mi-de-katani ad
she-yitkavnu shneihem k-echad, משמע דבעינן שידעו שהם מתכוונים לחליצה, mashma de-ba'inan she-yedu
she-hem mitkavnim le-chalitzah, right, that it would actually have to be clear
that that's their intent, not just something that looks like it's helping
him with his shoes, but maybe something is going on in my
head. No, it has to be intent, and maybe it even has
to be evident intent or contextually clear. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so what—so even if we saw her remove the shoe, what's the
issue? So the גמרא Gemara says, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's how
you have to read it. אף על גב דחזינן אין חוששין, af
al gav de-chazinan ein chosheshin, even if we saw her remove the
shoe, it's not a problem. אין חוששין שמא כוונו, ein chosheshin shema
kivnu, we're not concerned about what their intent was, okay? א', Alef,
we're not concerned they had that intent, or maybe you could even
go further like תוספות Tosafot suggests, even if they did have that
intent it wouldn't matter because that was not evident. The context was
not one of חליצה chalitzah and therefore it won't count as חליצה.
chalitzah. That's one answer. But then the גמרא Gemara says a more
מחמיר machmir answer. ואיכא דאמרי, ve-ika d'amri, others say, no. דווקא טעמא
דלא חזינן. davka ta'ama d'lo chazinan. The only reason it's not a
problem is we never saw her remove a shoe. הא חזינן, ha
chazinan, if we did see, חיישינן, chaishinan, we would be concerned. וקתני
בעי כוונה, ve-katani ba'i kavanah, how about the fact that it says
you need
intent? And again, the way תוספות Tosafot is reading this, and it
needs to be evident intent, so why should this be a problem?
הני מילי לאישתרויי לעלמא, hani milei le-ishtaru'ei l'alma, that's if it's to
actually say a good enough חליצה chalitzah to free her to marry
somebody else. אבל לאחים מיפסלא, aval l'achim mifsala, but a חליצה chalitzah
for the brothers' perspective,
it would invalidate her, right? Remember, it's so easy to knock out
the possibility of יבום, yibum, right? One brother does חליצה, chalitzah, one
brother does מאמר, ma'amar, knocks out the other brother. A brother gives
a גט, get, it knocks out all the brothers and so on.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying is you could have a middle-level
חליצה chalitzah that is maybe not good enough—real, it doesn't really work,
and she's not free to marry somebody else, but it's enough to—you'd
have
to redo it?
You'd have to redo it. Okay, but it's—but it's enough to prevent
any of the brothers from doing יבום. yibum. Right? So for it
to work it has to be evident that that's the intent, but
the גמרא Gemara allows for the possibility of a middle-level one that
would knock out the ability of יבום. yibum.
A second חליצה chalitzah is required to be מתיר matir her to
marry someone else.
Exactly. Okay, so okay. גמרא Gemara says, וקתני בעי כוונה, ve-katani ba'i
kavanah, oh, we just did that. אבל לאחים מיפסלא. aval l'achim mifsala.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, another statement
of רב יהודה אמר רב. Rav Yehuda amar Rav. It's very interesting
sometimes how you get certain אמוראים Amoraim that have areas that they
said a lot of things about, like a lot of רב יהודה
אמר רב's Rav Yehuda amar Rav's about חליצה. chalitzah. אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, סנדל התפור בפישתן אין חולצין
בו. sandal ha-tafur be-pishtan ein chaltzin bo. If you have a sandal
that is sewn with flax, right, רש"י Rashi has two explanations what
this means. It either means that the threading is flax or it
means that they basically have like a flax insert, sole insert that's
sewn into it that makes a cushion inside for the foot. So
that you can't use that. Why not? אין חולצין בו. ein chaltzin
bo.
שנאמר, she-ne'emar, because the verse says, ואנעילך תחש, va-eneilech tachash, and I
will sort of
be shoe you—שד—is shad to—isn't there a word to put on shoes
or שד shad is to remove shoes?
No, that's to put on.
Past tense, I will—so what's the current, the present tense? I will
shoe you. Anyway, I will shoe you—anyway, with תחש. tachash. Now, תחש
tachash is seen to be some type of an animal, right, או
רשימת תחשים, o reshimat tachashim, I have no idea what animal it
is.
A cow? Well, that wouldn't be good.
But anyway, it's—no, that's what the גמרא's Gemara's going to ask. It's
seen to be an animal that has skin and leather, and therefore
we're basically saying that the shoe has to be leather. Now, of
course, the point is the shoe has to be leather is one
thing and we know that from other הלכות halachot and the גמרא
Gemara will get to that at the end about יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, the emphasis of leather shoes, okay? But does that mean that
you can't even use a
flax threading? So what am I supposed to sew my shoes with?
It has to be leather straps. I mean, I guess so, that's
how they made sandals, right? It was leather—a leather bottom and leather
straps and you can't even have any anything sewn with something non-leather.
That's like extreme, which is why, which is why no—well, not an
insert is—at least a more radical change—a more significant change of the
shoe, right? So you understand why רש"י Rashi would prefer to read
it as no, you can't have a—like a linen insert. But to
say you can't even have linen threads is quite—is drastic,
okay? תימא תחש אין מידי אחריני לא? Teima tachash in midi achrini
lo? So, okay, just use—maybe only can use
תחש tachash skins? So the
גמרא Gemara says no. hit a middle state. אי נעל נעל ריבה,
ei na'al na'al ribba, if that's your, אפילו כל מידי נמי, afilu
kol midi nami, so you shouldn't require leather. No, אם כן תחש
מאי אהני? im ken tachash mai ahani? So what are we going
to get from תחש? tachash? Of course it's a פסוק pasuk in
יחזקאל, Yechezkel, but anyway, that enough informs us to limit it to
leather shoes. Obviously, there's a predisposition to see primary shoes, you know,
shoes are leather. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
בעי מיניה רב אלעזר מרב, ba'ei minei Rav Elazar meRav, רב אלעזר
Rav Elazar asked רב. Rav. הושט
של עור וטריסיותיו של שיער מהו? hushat shel or u-trisiotav shel sear
mahu? If it's made out of leather but its straps are שיער,
sear, hair, מהו? mahu? Now why should hair be different? We just
said it's got to be leather, maybe even the sewing has to
be leather. But here the point is that apparently this תחש tachash
has hair to it, right? So let's assume the תחש tachash is
something like, I don't know, a sheep. Okay. So therefore I could
say, well, maybe I could have a leather shoe with wool straps
because, you know, because sheep have wool too. So maybe that's okay.
So what's the story? אמר ליה ומי לא קרינא ביה ואנעלך תחש?
amar leh u-mi lo karina beih ve-analach tachash? Wouldn't that fit in
the פסוק? pasuk? Yeah, that should be fine because hair at least
is consistent with this תחש. tachash. Okay. אי הכי כולו של שיער
נמי? ei hachi kulo shel sear nami? All right, then make the
whole thing out of this. No. ההוא קרקא מיקרי. hahu karka mikrei.
That's called קרקא karka or whatever, which רש״י Rashi basically says, I
don't know what רש״י Rashi says, but basically it's like,
that's more like a slipper than it is a shoe. How do
they translate קרקא karka there?
A slipper. All right, fine. That's not serious enough, that's not protective
enough. Okay, so we basically come up with this idea that you
need a leather as the main part and maybe you can use
some other animal product, but not clear exactly what, because remember פשתן,
pishtan, right? It's worth mentioning, פשתן pishtan is not just not leather,
פשתן pishtan is from the plant kingdom. Okay. So can you use
wool straps? What does the גמרא Gemara mean by שיער? sear? Specifically
שיער sear like
goat's hair? But maybe things from the animal kingdom would be
okay. So exactly what the parameters are are not 100% clear what's
included in this שיער, sear, but the shoe itself has to be
leather.
Okay,
מיקרי. mikrei. אמר ליה רב כהנא לשמואל. amar leh Rav Kahana leShmuel.
רב כהנא Rav Kahana said to שמואל. Shmuel. ממי דהאי וחלצה נעלו
מעל רגלו משלוף הוא? mimmay de-hai ve-chaltzah na'alo me-al raglo mishluf hu?
How do you know removing the shoe, the word חלץ chalatz means
to
remove? דכתיב וחלצו את האבנים אשר בהן הנגע, de-chtiv ve-chiltzu et ha-avanim
asher ba-hen ha-naga, remove the stones that have the, you know, the
spot of צרעת. tzara'at. ואימא זירוזי הוא? ve-eima ziruzei hu? Maybe the
word חלץ chalatz means to like arm, to gird, דכתיב de-chtiv or
like gird with strength or to arm, דכתיב החלצו מאתכם אנשים לצבא.
de-chtiv hechalitzu me-it-chem anashim la-tzava. Arm for you, gird for you men
for the army. So what would it mean that וחלצה נעלו מעל
רגלו? ve-chaltzah na'alo me-al raglo? So the גמרא Gemara says somehow, I
don't know, the גמרא Gemara will sort of say, it means maybe
it means puts the shoe on, like get him ready to go
out to war. I know, it's hard to know exactly how the
גמרא Gemara would have interpreted the פסוק, pasuk, but something like, help
get him ready to walk, put his shoe on his foot or
something. I don't know. Anyway, it's exploring is the word חלץ. chalatz.
Okay. So it says, התם נמי שלופי. hatam nami shalufi. No, there
too, the word to prepare for war is rooted in the word
of remove because it means remove from the house,
שלופי מביצא לקרבא shalufi mi-beisa le-karba and go out to war. It'd
be interesting, I didn't get a chance to check the BDB, like
whether these are really ultimately come from a similar root, the word
חלץ chalatz to remove and the word חלץ chalatz to be ready
for war. It'd be interesting to see. Somebody could check it up,
BDB is online. דהא כתיב יחלץ עני בעניו. de-ha ktiv yachallaitz ani
be-onyo.
Doesn't it say that God will gird the poor person in his
poverty, like maybe give him strength or something like that? So doesn't
it mean remove, it means to give strength? No. בשכר עניו יחלצו
מדינה של גיהנם. bischar onyo yechaltzu me-dina shel Gehennom. Because of his,
you know, suffering, he will be removed from the judgment of גיהנם.
Gehennom. אלא הא דכתיב חונה מלאך ה' סביב ליראיו ויחלצם. ela ha
de-chtiv choneh mal'ach Hashem saviv li-reyav vi-yachaltzem.
The angel of God encamps around those that fear him and, again,
we would say gives them a strength, you know, but how do
you read it to remove? No. בשכר יראיו יחלצם מדינה של גיהנם.
bischar yereyav yechaltzem me-dina shel Gehennom. Because they're fearful, they fear God,
they get removed, they get saved from the judgment of גיהנם.
Gehennom. וקרא כדריש לחילוץ עצמות. ve-kra kidrish le-chilutz atzamot.
Yeah, the גמרא Gemara is going to get to חילוץ עצמות. chilutz
atzamot. ואלא הא דכתיב ועצמותיך יחליץ, ve-ela ha de-chtiv ve-atzmotecha yachallitz,
his bones he, you know, you know God will strengthen. ואמר רב
אלעזר זו מעולה שבברכות. ve-amar Rav Elazar zu me'ula sheba-berachot. This is
the best of the blessings, as Michael said, we say חילוץ עצמות,
chilutz atzamot, strength. ואמר רבא זירוזי גרמי. ve-amar Rava ziruzei garmei. The
sort
of strengthening of the bones, and that's what it means. So you
see that it means strengthening and you can't say removing of the
bones. So the גמרא Gemara says, אין משמע הכא ומשמע הכא. in,
mashma hacha u-mashma hacha. All right, I concede it. יחלוץ yachallotz can
mean remove and it can mean to strengthen. דהא הכא de-ha hacha
but here it has to mean to remove. אי סלקא דעתך זירוזי
הוא, ei salka dach-tach ziruzei hu, if it meant to strengthen, אם
כן ליכתוב רחמנא וחלצה נעלו ברגלו. im ken lichtov rachmana ve-chaltzah na'alo
be-raglo.
Put the shoe on his foot. you know, foot. אי כתיב רחמנא
*ee ksiv Rachmana* ברגלו *beraglo*, now if it had said on his
foot, הוה אמינא *hava amina* ברגלו אין בשוקו לא *beraglo in beshoko
lo*, only the foot, not including the calf. כתב רחמנא *ktav Rachmana*
מעל רגלו *me-al raglo* that even like put it on the part
above the foot. You put it on the calf, like you wrap
the straps around the calf. דאפילו בשוקו *d'afilu beshoko*. No. If that's
all the Torah wanted to say, אם כן *im kein* ליכתוב רחמנא
*lichtov Rachmana* במעל רגלו *b'me-al raglo*. Put on the shoe on the
part above his foot. מאי *mai* מעל *me-al*? From his רגלו *raglo*.
שמע מינה *shma mina* משלף הוא *mishlaf hu*.
It means to remove. Let this be one more sentence to end
this up. אמר ליה ההוא מינא לרבן גמליאל *amar lei hahu mina
l'Rabban Gamliel*. A certain heretic, often meaning a Jewish Christian, said to
Rabban Gamliel: עמא דחלץ מריה מיניה *ama de-chalatz marei minei*. You are
a nation your God has abandoned you, right? Classic sort of, you
know, Christian polemic. Your God has abandoned you. דכתיב *dichsiv*. How do
I know? He did חליצה *chalitza* to you. He didn't want to
have anything to do with you. You are the, you know, you're,
you know, your husband died and God's abandoned you and he's now
gone ahead and found himself a new wife or something, you know,
the Christians. So, how do you know this? דכתיב *dichsiv*: בצאנם ובבקרם
ילכו לבקש את השם *betzonam u-be-vekaram yelchu le-vakesh et Hashem*. They will
go out with their herds to seek out God. ולא ימצאו *ve-lo
yimtza'u*. And they will not find him. חלץ מהם *chalatz me-hem*. He
has removed himself from them. Okay? So, you see, he's done חליצה
*chalitza* to you. אמר ליה *amar lei*. So he said back to
him, "No. שוטה *shoteh*, idiot. מי כתיב חלץ להם *mi ksiv chalatz
la-hem*?
It didn't say that. Who who does the חליצה *chalitza*, right? It's
the woman that does the חליצה *chalitza*, right? So it didn't say
חלץ להם *chalatz la-hem*, that somehow, you know, God had that that
he had been the subject of the חליצה *chalitza* from בני ישראל
*Bnei Yisrael*. חלץ מהם כתיב *chalatz me-hem ksiv*. Okay, again, it's not
exactly clear to me how why he would do it one way
or the other way. Anyway, but it says basically it's sort of
God is the man in this scenario and he is the one
that has somehow done the חליצה *chalitza* from them, meaning he's done
חליצה *chalitza* to them. ואילו יבמה דחלץ לה אחי מידי מששא אית
בה *v'ilu yevama de-chalatz la achi midei mashasha it bah*? And if
a and if the brothers did the remove or did the חליצה
*chalitza* to the יבמה *yevama*, to the sister-in-law, it would be silly.
So you know so it's basically saying that it says the
people rejected God not the other way around,
right? Yes,
the Jewish people did the חליצה *chalitza* to הקדוש ברוך הוא *Hakadosh
Baruch Hu* as it were, and not הקדוש ברוך הוא *Hakadosh Baruch
Hu* did חליצה *chalitza* to the Jewish people. That's my yeah.
But the problem is that God is cast as the male and
therefore I think the way it's reading it, although I agree I
was having a problem with the grammar, but I think the way
רש"י *Rashi* was reading it is that God is the male and
it's saying God might have done a חליצה *chalitza* to us but
it was silly and meaningless. It was all it was all because
of it says מהם *me-hem*, right? He received חליצה *chalitza* from them.
It's בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael* they were doing yeah.
I know, but then it is but then the point should be
needs to be emphasized in according to that is that בני ישראל
*Bnei Yisrael* is being seen of as the man. Right, but I
don't think that's how רש"י *Rashi* read it.
No, God is the man and and the woman does the one
who does the חליצה *chalitza*, right?
So then that's a binding one. But the whole point was that
it wasn't a binding חליצה *chalitza*. It was right? It's not a
binding his point is it wasn't a binding חליצה *chalitza* because the
man did it to the woman. So the question is how is
he reading the verse? Is he reading the verse that בני ישראל
*Bnei Yisrael* did the חליצה *chalitza* and בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael* are
being cast as the man, right?
As the mean was saying that like God rejected you, it's like
no, we rejected God.
Yeah, but Rabbi, I'm just saying for
that to be
the case, the his point is the point is
he's saying a חליצה *chalitza* done by the man to remove the
shoe of the woman is not binding, and that's what this verse
is saying, that the man did the חליצה *chalitza*. That's his basic
point in terms of the חליצה *chalitza* model. So the question is:
is he saying God is the man and God did the חליצה
*chalitza* to us, which you were bothered by because then it's a
meaningless פסוק *pasuk*, what does that mean? So you're saying, "No, no,
in this פסוק *pasuk* בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael* is being cast as
the man and we did the חליצה *chalitza* to God, we rejected
God but it was not it was not meaningful." I think that
that's a satisfying read, but it basically winds up casting בני ישראל
*Bnei Yisrael* as the man in this scenario. Okay, we will end
with this time.
We have an image of God as a woman in ישעיה *Yeshaya*?
Yeah.
Yeah, you do sometimes.